[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net SC radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
[Music]
software welcome to software engineering
radio I'm your host bries shanit today I
will be discussing professional skills
for software Engineers with Charles
humble Charles is a IT industry veteran
we almost 30 years of experience a
former software engineer architect and
CTO Charles has worked as a senior
leader and executive of both technology
and content groups Charles is an
experienced commissioning editor was
infoq editor and Chief and was Chief
editor for container Solutions Charles
writes regularly for the new stack or
and other Publications and has spoken at
multiple International conferences
Charles welcome to software engineering
radio thank you very much it's lovely to
be here Charles you have written a
series of shortcuts that will enable
developers to improve their
communication critical thinking
documentation and networking skills what
drove you to write these series of
shortcuts there's a kind of a long
answer to that and a short answer to
that so the short answer is it's a
project that I had in my head for years
and about nine months ago I pitched it
to O'Reilly and with them I kind of
found a publisher for it and the basic
idea was I wanted to provide a set of
resources for junior and mid-level
software Engineers that cover areas that
you're not generally taught at
University but that I think are really
important if you want to get into more
senior roles so essentially you can
think of it as a set of things that I
wish someone had told me when I got my
first promotion and that was one answer
to the question but the other was kind
of reflecting over the course of my
career so I learned to program in the
1980s on 8bit computers so mainly the
BBC model B and Momo 64 and at the time
we had magazines where people would sh
things they'd learn how to do so with
the Commodore 64 for example the screen
had a border around it which you
couldn't do anything with I mean you
could change the color of it but you
couldn't put Graphics into it and then
at some point someone figured out how to
put Graphics or put Sprites into the
Border by using a bit of assembly code
and interrup timing trick and then they
described how they'd done it in the
magazine which meant that we could all
learn it and that was kind of my first
exposure to computers in the industry
really was how I learned to program and
then when I joined the industry as a
professional which was in the sort of
1994 I think that was sort of didn't
really happen anymore it was like code
had become this kind of secret thing
that we didn't really talk about and
obviously open sources has changed that
to some extent but I feel very strongly
as an industry we need to get better at
sharing our knowledge and our experience
because so much in the industry is quite
kind of nent and poorly
understood years later as you said I
joined infu as Chief editor which was a
position I had for about six years and
infu has this really interesting model
in that essentially what they do is they
take programmers and they train them how
to be news writers and then how to write
news so most tech websites will have
Tech journalists so professional
journalists who writ about technology
while as infu has professional
developers who have learned how to write
so I spent a lot of time basically
training Engineers how to write better
and what I realized was an awful lot of
them have this kind of weird fear of
writing because they've been told at
some point that weren't good at it that
they didn't have a gift for Words which
just seems like a terribly
unnecessary burden to carry through life
and it's nonsense programming and
writing are both crafts and therefore
like any craft they can be learned so
about two years ago I wrote a conference
talk called writing for nerds and
essentially what I did was I talked
about writing and how do it and I gave
it a couple of times I gave it at go to
and I gave it at devox in the UK and
each time I had a packed room which
surprised me but it kind of implied that
there uh people who were interested in
this so I kind of thought well maybe I
should do some writing about writing for
engineers writing as an engineer rather
than writing for an audience of
Engineers and then I sort of found
myself reflecting on writing and on the
other skills so communication systems
thinking and so on and how all of those
things sort of intersect so that was
really the longer on so that was really
the starting point and as I said I
pitched it to O'Reilly we played around
with it for a while and eventually ended
up with a set of these 14 connected
articles so what they call shortcuts
between about a thousand and about 2,000
words on
average and that's the stuff that you
find on the a Riley platform and they
seem to have been quite popular I've had
some lovely feedback on them at least so
they've found an audience and hopefully
it's a useful resource for people that
makes perfect sense we'll Deep dive into
each of these themes over the course of
this podcast what are some of the common
communication challenges that Engineers
face within teams
so there are a couple of different
things that come up all the time one of
them is meeting proliferation and that
happens particularly in remote settings
so that's basically where you feel like
your entire day is filled with nothing
but meetings essentially and there are a
variety of reasons why that breaks flow
for
people
so part of dealing with that is thinking
about the where synchronous
communication so meetings whether that's
personal or
online is the right thing is the correct
thing to do and where asynchronous
communication whether that's VI slack or
email or something like that might be a
better method I think in general the
sort of point with this sort of stuff
with communication in general is to be
very deliberate about what you're doing
and why you're doing it so think about
if I'm going to have a meeting who needs
to be there can I put an agenda together
so people know what to expect how long
do I think I need kind of avoid we sort
of automatically tend to default to an
hour or something does it need to be an
hour or can it be 40 minutes so those
some of the things I think it's very
helpful to have some sort of actual
communication policy so these are the
channels we use when we need an Urgent
Response these are the channels we need
when we use when we need a less Urgent
Response an awful lot of this stuff as I
say is really about being deliberate and
thinking about what is the right method
of communication to use for this
particular thing I also have a whole
section on empathy which again I think
is really key to a lot of this which I
can talk about a bit as well but yeah
just thinking about what's the most
efficient way to get this across to a
team of people is probably the starting
point right how does empathy help
improve collaboration between engineers
especially in high pressure or tense
situations yeah I think empathy is
incredibly important I think there are a
whole variety of different situations
where empathy really really matters but
anywhere where communication can be a
little bit difficult or if you're
thinking in product senses where you're
trying to understand what the customer
experience is like understanding how to
so I'm using empathy here to mean
basically taking someone else's
perspective and knowing how to do that
it's incredibly helpful when you're
designing products it's also incredibly
helpful in any situation where you have
teen conflict or disagreements between
team members it's incredibly helpful
when you're working with stakeholders
that maybe aren't in it or maybe in a
business background I really really
think it's absolutely key and it's
something that you can learn how to do I
think lots of us kind of know how to do
it and itively but not everybody does
there are exceptions to this but in
general there is actually quite strong
evidence that empathy in the sense I'm
using it here is a skill that most
people can learn how to do so I think
again taking the time to do that is
helpful it's helpful when you're working
on products it's helpful when you're
working on teams and so much of what we
do is collaboration at the end of the
day and empathy is a really key thing
for being able to collaborate
effectively couple of thoughts come to
mind but before I jump to the next
question do you have any techniques to
improve
empathy yeah I actually go through
something of a practical exercise in for
learning how to do it in the relevant
shortcut but in brief the first thing to
do is to actually start reflecting on
your own responses so if you respond to
something in a slightly unexpected way
take some time to reflect on why that is
for me personally I have a thing that I
tend to have quite
strong emotional responses so my
emotions get quite big on me quite
easily and so it's something that I had
to learn to do in order to be able to
control my emotions and you can treat it
like a data point like you might in a
malfunctioning system or something where
you basically sort of step back and go
well that's a weird response why am I
responding that way so that's the first
thing get used to your own responses the
second thing is to get much better at
listening and really listening so being
properly attentive trying not to tra
when someone's speaking when they finish
try and reflect on what they've said and
make sure you've really understood it so
you can use techniques like mirroring
where you basically rephrase something
back to somebody so did you mean this
don't be afraid to ask questions if
you're not sure and that by the way
that's so valuable because we are as
human beings we are so distracted all
the time so it's super valuable in a
work context but actually it's amazingly
valuable in your personal relationships
as well people really value that sense
of being properly listened to and
properly heard so those things are a
really good starting point a lot of this
is just about making stuff that you may
do instinctively a conscious practice
and actually thinking through what it is
I'm doing and why am I doing it and
that's the stuff that really makes a
difference so let me try mirroring your
response to make sure that I've
understood what you've said mhm so the
key techniques of improving empathy that
stood out for me one was reflect on your
response to ensure that you're able to
control your emotions number two was be
better at listening which is be really
attentive and do not interrupt third was
mirroring summarize what you have
understood to make sure the other person
agrees to that and the third most
important point was don't be afraid to
ask questions mhm continuing with the
theme of
communication you also mentioned that
when you're communicating with
stakeholders it's important to Pivot
these conversations around outcomes why
is that as a rule of fun business people
don't care very much about technology
and as technologists that's quite a hard
lesson in a way that's quite a hard
thing to accept because we as industry
professionals get very excited about the
way our systems are built the
architecture the cleanness of it the
expressiveness of our code and that sort
of thing the business doesn't care about
any of that stuff what they do care
about is they care about results they
care about what the consequences of what
you're doing are so I have in my
consulting job I have had so many
conversations with people that have been
along the lines of I'm trying to get the
business to sponsor me to pay down
technical debt on this application and
the business won't do that and it's so
frustrating and you're like well have
you explained to them what that even
means because if you haven't they
probably have no idea in fact technical
data is really bizarre to me because we
think of it as quite a useful mass for
but it really isn't I don't think it
helps anybody I I mean even it people
I'm not sure if you actually sat down a
bunch of programmers and said what does
technical debt really mean I suspect a
lot of them would struggle to really
describe it other Beyond you know
getting rid of things I don't like the
term is every bid is meaningless to a
business stakeholder so if you frame
things in a way that makes sense so in
the shortcut I use the example of I
can't exactly remember but it's
something like we've got 10% of our
customers are banding us on the Android
app at checkout and we think that's
because of
the app is freezing or crashing or
something we think that's costing us x
amount in revenue and we reckon it will
take us about four weeks to try and fix
it and you as an IT person know what I'm
actually going to be doing is fixing a
bunch of accumulated debt in that
application which is there because I
wrote the thing too quickly in the first
place but the important point now is
that the business has a reason to
sponsor you to do it and a reasonable
understanding of what the expected
outcome is and it also of course means
they can you to account so if you go
away for four weeks and come back and
the app is still crashing or customers
are still abandoning you at the checkout
you've then got a reason to go and look
again and go okay well that didn't work
so what's really going on here because
we actually sponsored you to solve the
problem so that's the point it's getting
away from this idea that at the end I
don't like the division between the
business and it because I think it's UNH
helpful at the end of the day we're all
part of the business right but it's just
thinking about expressing things in a
way that makes sense to the other
person's context so they can make
informed choices and right choices and
hopefully the choices may be the ones
you want or at least if they're not the
ones you want there's a good reason the
other part of that is if you can't come
up with a business justification maybe
you shouldn't be doing it at all you
know if you're sitting there thinking I
don't know I want to rewrite our entire
application in rust or go or something
and it's currently written in Java and
you can't justify that in business terms
well maybe you shouldn't doing it and
that's not a bad thing you might not
like it but it's not necessarily a bad
thing so I think that's the other sort
of side of the same coin I think
technology dep is a very good example
and how pivoting to outcomes gives us a
mechanism to measure it the delivery in
your shortcut you also give a very good
example on why it's actually important
to talk to customers most of the
software Engineers are introverts don't
want to generalize them but that's the
case why is it important to talk to
customers I had a really
great experience on this very early on
my career actually it was for a retail
bank in the UK and it was specifically
for the call center and this particular
retail bank I can't name them
unfortunately but basically there were
two banks that had merged and they had
two separate Mainframe systems that were
were two separate banking engines and
they had their call center staff
basically sitting in front of a pair of
green screens so think sort of
1970s dumb terminals with incredibly
cryptic information on them and we were
bought in so my team was bought in to
basically replace that with a webbased
easier to learn prettier looking front
end and that all sounded fine and we did
a bunch of work and we had some
beautiful beautiful looking web screens
and we thought this is absolutely
amazing and then we took it into the
call center for the first time and the
call center absolutely hated what we
done it was really kind of shocking they
just loed it and the reason that they
loed it turned out to be that the way a
banking call center typically works you
go through a process called idmv so
basically you ring the bank you go
through a verification process while
that's happening in the background the
information about that customer is being
loaded up so by the time you clear idmv
and land on a call center land with a
human in a call center that human has
information about you in front of them
with the green screens the call center
person had literally everything every
answer to every question you were going
to ask them on one of two screens and
they could all tab between the two of
them well as with our system they had
you know maybe 10 or 15 or 20 different
places they had to go to get the same
information our system was much much
easier to learn because the green
screens had a learning curve like a
brick wall but the point was that once
you knew what all the cryptic acronyms
meant all you needed was one of the two
screens and what was so interesting
about it was the call center staff were
being measured on how quickly they Clos
the calls and yes the learning curve was
harder but with the green screens the
time it took them to close each call was
much much lower because they didn't have
to go off and keep clicking and looking
in multiple places and if we just spent
a bit of time sitting down and talking
to them in the first place and
understanding what their world looks
like we would had a much better idea of
how to design the web system in the
first place but as it turned out that
hadn't really happened there were a lot
of people who just kind of assumed they
knew and knew that this would be better
it's a really really good example so
often I think your understanding of
somebody else's world and what somebody
else might want from a system is just
going to be wrong and unless you take
the time to TCH them to understand their
position you're going to end up building
the wrong thing and then it doesn't
matter how well you build it it doesn't
matter how good the code is how
efficient it is how good the
architecture is you've built the wrong
thing and everyone's going to hate it so
it's important not only to talk to your
customers but also to frequently
demonstrate what you've built let's
transition to the next set of or theme
of shortcuts which is around critical
thinking skills in your shortcut about
systems thinking you give a very good
personal example about how you
transition from linear thinking to
systems thinking can you walk our
listeners through this journey yes so
again it kind of links back to the commo
64 experience which I mentioned right at
the beginning so when I was learning to
program the programs I created were
linear and they were easy enough to
reason about and what I didn't I didn't
notice at the time but what I was
learning was a very specific approach to
thinking about software and that
approach is called reductionism I can
summarize that basically as being the
idea that a complex system is just the
sum of its
parts what was interesting was when I
worked on my first distributed system so
that was building an internet app for UK
High Street Bank in the early
2000s and with that banking system we
basically had it was a message keing
based system so it was running on top of
IBM mq series and we had a set of what
we called Elements which were like small
programs that basically read they were
single threaded and they read messages
off a key and that was brilliant because
they were very easy to understand as
individual bits of software and you
could scale them up and down very easily
because all you needed to do was to
start more instances of them and then
you would be draining the queue quicker
so that was fantastic but what was odd
about it for me was that I found the
business of understanding what the
system was doing became much harder so
even though I could understand what the
individual elements what the individual
little Q serving Q reading programs were
doing I was very very hard to get my
head around what the overall system was
doing and the reason for that was
because all of the complexity was
actually in the interactions between the
different elements and how they behaved
and if you think about modern software
that's basically what we do so the
majority of modern software is built
from a set of what are event-driven
independently Deployable services that
can evolve at different rates and what
that means is that the skills we learn
through reduction they're still useful
they're very useful when you're creating
Individual Services but they sort of
fall down when we're trying to reason
about how the system as a whole behaves
that was the kind of example that I give
in the in the shortcut and it's really
paying attention to the relationships
between things so rather than with a
microservice understanding what the
individual microservice has done is
generally pretty straightforward but
understanding how the microservices as a
whole behave is more complex and it's
complex because you get these sort of
emergent behaviors as a consequence of
the way the systems interact another way
to think about it is the system is no
longer with some of its parts but it's
the product of its interactions so yeah
that's the example I give the shortcut
the other thing I liked about your
shortcuts is the links that you provide
they're very relevant and make for very
interesting reading I read one
particular quote which stays in my mind
I'm not sure if it was in the actual
shortcut or if it was one of the links
that I followed through it basically
said that because you understand
understand one you think that you also
understand two because one and one make
two but you forget that you also need to
understand and I think I do quote that
in the actual shortcut it's from danella
Meadow her book which is kind of a
classic text which is called thinking in
systems thinking in systems is it's not
an IT book as such but it is a book
about systems thinking and it's really
really good and yeah I love that quote
too I also link actually to another book
by Diana monalia called Learning Systems
thinking which is kind of taking some of
Den's ideas and applying them in a more
it oriented way so that's another really
really good text on the subject and
there's a quote from her that I really
like which is the role of a systems
architect is to synthesize ideas not
dictate what to think so my goal is to
empower people to thrive because I
depend on everyone's knowledge to
succeed which is very much what a system
does the role of a systems AR is to
synthesize ideas and not dictate what to
think a very relevant quote a very good
one something which I will remember as
well moving on to feedback can you
expand on what role does feedback play
in sharpening an engineer critical
thinking skills so I can give you a very
personal story about feedback actually
so around 2008 I think I was lead
architect for a startup in the insurance
sector and it was a very intense job it
was very enjoyable I had 50 or so people
in the room they were all working flat
out trying to build basically a life
insurance system in a box and I had a
huge disagreement with one of the
business analysts on the project and I
thought I was just putting my point
across but my manager pulled me aside
afterwards and said you know basically
we hired you because of your passion but
you need to realize that you are
shutting down discussion and I was so
cross and the reason I was so cross was
because I knew he was right and I had to
reflect on it quite a bit because it was
one of those things I had to learn to
manage about my own personality because
I genuinely had no idea that that was
how I was coming across so I owe him I
owe that particular manager a huge death
of gratitude for letting me know that I
was out of
line and giving me the opportunity to
reflect on that and correct it I think
in general as managers giving that sort
of feedback is really hard right none of
us like doing it I do not like doing it
and when you receive that kind of
feedback that's really uncomfortable as
well right no one wants to be told that
kind of thing but I think it's one of
those things it's so valuable for people
to be able to tell you aspects or the
impact of aspects of your behavior that
you might not otherwise be aware of and
I think that in the context of critical
thinking critical thinking is a lot of
that's really about weighing evidence so
you can think of it as an example of I'm
suddenly been given a bit of evidence
about myself but I wasn't really aware
of and then I can go through the same
kind of process in terms of evaluating
that taking it on board and thinking
well how do I course correct that
particular bit of behavior are there any
exercises or techniques that Engineers
can use to develop their critical
thinking skills yes there are there's
essentially a set of things that make
critical thinking up so a big chunk of
it is really thinking about how you
evaluate so with problem solving
basically the secret of problem solving
is to come up with a set of potential
Solutions rather than just one the
mistake a lot of us make early in our
careers is we come up with a solution
and we go that's the solution and we go
from there the right thing to do is
always to come up with a set of
potential Solutions and then try and
solve those and then try and decide
which one of those to use with critical
thinking there's a bunch of methods that
you can use to do that so the best one
is to write an AB test the problem of
doing an AB test for everything it's
kind of like a Best in Class thing but
they're also quite heavyweight they're
quite difficult to design well and
frustratingly if you don't design them
well and even sometimes when you do they
don't necessarily give you a
particularly clear-cut answer so the
second thing you can do is obviously
look at correlations in your existing
data it's less timec consuming it's not
always obvious though why two things are
correlated so that's a bit problematic
you can also look at historical
arguments so has anyone studied this
before if they have what conclusions
they reach and then you can also have
the collective experience of a team to
draw on and anotal evidence and those
sorts of things so it's again going back
to this idea of a lot of these things
are about deliberate practice so a
deliberate practice with critical
thinking is ask the question form a
hypothesis gather and weigh the evidence
and basically do those things in a
logical sequence and the thing about
learning that approach and learning that
skill is it has incredibly broad
applicability so I've used it when
making investment decisions at an
executive level I've used it when
designing products and features I've
used it when dealing with a problem in a
team and trying to effectively like
debugging a team either used it when
evaluating you know should I be using
dependency injection for this or should
I just you know solve the same problem
with half a dozen factores and I use it
all the time now when I'm interviewing
people and writing and that sort of
thing there a really help ful technique
it does take practice and it really is
just one of those things if you know
what it is you're trying to do you just
have to practice and get better at it
but you will get better at it with time
and it absolutely is
worthwhile another quote which stood out
for me was your quote in the shortcut on
problem solving and it basically went
like a problem well stated is a problem
half solved I thought that was a
beautiful quote the actual quote is from
GM I think and yeah it's a lovely quote
so it it comes from Charles kering and
he was an inventor he was head of
research at GM and yeah he says a
problem well stated is a problem half
solved which I think is a great great qu
can you expand on the four-step process
that you have described in your shortcut
on problem
solving yeah so I describe a kind of
four-step process and that four-step
process works with almost any problem so
we're starting point is to make sure
you've actually identified and can
actually articulate what the problem is
and I think so often we make a mistake
of kind of diving in straight away
without actually starting up front and
going you know what am I expecting to
happen and what's actually happening so
if you think about a bug what am I
actually seeing what's the thing that
I'm observing that makes me believe this
is a bug and what should it be doing
having that in your head when you start
is a really really good starting Point
once you've got that the second step is
then to go and basically gather
information and how you do that will
depend a lot on the actual nature of the
problem you're trying to solve it might
be looking at the documentation it might
be looking at log files or commit
history or something like that then at
that point you start coming up with
potential Solutions and as I said
earlier what you want to do is you want
to come up with several possible
solutions rather than just one and try
not to dismiss an idea too quickly I
think it's very tempting to go oh well
that obviously won't work and if you
find yourself doing that spend a bit of
time thinking well why won't it work
because again we all have kind of
confirmation biases and particular kinds
of thinking patterns that we get very
used to with coming up with Solutions I
use a technique called confessional
programming quite often it's sometimes
called rubber ducking and the term
rubber ducking comes from the pragmatic
programmer book the basic idea is to try
and explain the problem that I'm having
to somebody else and that might be a
colleague that might be a fellow
programmer I will sometimes explain
stuff to my wife I've also though
explained stuff to my very old cat who
is probably fast asleep on another chair
in my office or something because it
doesn't really matter who you're
explaining it to the point is by
articulating it by explaining it quite
often you'll get to the point of going
oh hang on it's like as you explaining
it you suddenly realized something about
it that you hadn't realized before I
think also there's something there about
trying to articulate something out loud
which triggers a slightly different part
of your brain and makes you see things
sometimes in a slightly different way so
that's helpful and then at that point
you can move to implementation so once
you've got a set of solutions you've
pick the solution you want to try you
can then start the implementation of
that solution one thing with that and
again obviously it depends on the nature
of the problem but one thing with the
implementation is sometimes when you
start implementing you'll effectively
realize oh hang on I'm going down the
the wrong path and that's okay right
that's fine be prepared to go back and
go okay well that didn't work maybe this
is I've got more information hopefully
and therefore this other method might be
a better method for solving the same
problem so to summarize the four steps
are step one would be to identify and
articulate what the problem is step two
is to gather information about the
problem whether that's through
documentation talking to end users step
three would be to come up with potential
Solutions
and over here you also talk about a
technique called as rubber ducking in
your shortcut you also mentioned this is
where you challenge where the problem
really needs to be solved yes absolutely
and step four is where you start coding
your preferred
solution yes yes absolutely absolutely
now we'll move on to the next theme of
shortcuts which is around networking
skills when we had a pre-recording
discussion you mentioned how networking
personally help you in your career I
found your story about your engagement
with infoq and your progress to become
its Chief Editor to be very interesting
can you walk a listeners through that
yes absolutely so I originally started
as a newswriter on the Java keq for infq
a very long time ago and what actually
happened was I sent an email to the
person who was the head of the Java
Queue at the time who was a guy called
Scott toop and I sent him an email
asking him why he hadn't covered
something called Google web toolkit and
Google web toolkit was a kind of
transpiler from java to JavaScript and I
thought it was interesting so I sent him
an email saying I was surprised you
didn't write about this and I got a very
Charming email back from him saying
basically here are my reasons why we
didn't cover it and by the way have you
ever thought about being a News writer
and I honestly hadn't and I thought well
that's very bizarre maybe I should give
it a g because it sounds interesting and
so I started writing news for them I
quite quickly discovered that I had a
bit of an aptitude for it
and then I became lead Java editor when
Scott stepped down and I was lead Java
editor I think if I remember rightly for
about five or six years and then they
approached me and asked me if I would
take the chief editor job on and I
actually turned it down originally and I
turned it down for a couple of different
reasons one was that I was doing a
startup at the time that was we were
basically positioning for acquisition so
I was very very busy doing all of the
work that that implies but the second
reason is because I'm actually dyslexic
and the idea of being a chief editor and
dyslexic just seem so incredibly
unlikely that I couldn't kind of Imagine
doing it so anyway I did the startup the
startup was indeed acquired I did a year
for a large consulting firm who acquired
us and at the end of that year I
desperately wanted to do something else
and I had a rather drunken conversation
with my wife one New Year's Eve where I
said basically I want to do something
else I'm not quite sure what it is and
she said well what about that Chief
editor job um you know are they still
looking for somebody have they found
anybody I don't know I don't think they
have so I went back to Floyd marinescu
who is the co-founder of se4 media which
is the company that owns in and said I
finished my startup and I am available
and i' let's talk to you and we ended up
having two or three meetings and then he
said fine why didn't you come and do the
job and what was so interesting about it
was genuinely I had no idea what being
Chief editor really meant or what it
would involve and it turned out that a
lot of the skills that I learned as a
CTO particularly
weren't that relevant in quite the same
way a lot of running something like infq
is about you have to make many many many
decisions but they're all quite small
and in and of themselves they feel quite
inconsequential but over time they have
a sort of accumulative effect so the
trick is you basically have to learn to
be constantly thinking about where am I
trying to go and does this little tiny
decision I'm making over here move me
closer to that end goal or further away
typically what happens with the CTO type
role is you have fewer decisions to make
but the decisions you do have to make
tend to be a lot more bigger but they're
also a lot more obvious in terms of what
they not obvious necessarily but the you
understand what the impact is in a way
that's harder with something where
you've got a lot of small decisions to
make but it was a really fascinating job
I had a very happy five or six years
there it was absolutely fascinating and
doing infu more broadly just introduced
me to so many people and raised my my
own profile and opened up so many doors
for me in terms of other things that I
could go on and do and that was yeah
that was really really great experience
I think thanks for sharing that very
interesting story with our listeners
Charles so the whole journey with infoq
started with you reaching out
proactively to the Java Q editor asking
him a relevant question about the Google
web toolkit the challenge most engineer
pH is in making that initial contact or
how does one overcome that initial
hesitation of putting the thoughts out
there especially if they feel they don't
have much to contribute oh that's such
an interesting question so again it
depends a little bit what medium you
mean if we're talking about writing
there's effectively like a little bit of
a hierarchy of places where you can
publish so obviously one of those would
be a self-published Blog right no one's
got control over that other than you you
can basically publish what you like the
next level up from that would be
something like a company blog and the
next level up from that would be an
article for an actual publisher so Riley
or infq or a new stack or somebody like
that and if you're looking to start
writing then honestly the best way to
learn it is just to start doing it and
be a little bit self-critical so maybe
start by writing some stuff for a Blog
that you publish yourself or a lot of
companies have blogs or or Tech blogs
that you could maybe write for and with
a bit of luck if it's a company blog
there'll be someone that can actually
give you a bit of feedback and review
what you're writing and yeah just get a
bit of a feel for it get a bit of
experience for it and then once you've
done that then maybe you could think
about reaching out to somebody like infq
or ay or whoever it is with infu they do
have a news trainer program and the News
trainer program is brilliant so what you
can do if you go on the infu site
there'll be a contribute button
somewhere and if you can find that it'll
take you through the steps but basically
you say I'm interested in writing about
this topic and then what they'll do is
they will pay you with a journalism
Professor so someone who can basically
de like sort of basic journalism 101
type teaching and a subject matter
person who can help you with
understanding the audience and the
technical aspects of it and just by
doing that and writing on a regular
Cadence so maybe writing a 500w News
Post once a week or something like that
you will get so much better I completely
understand the thing of it it can be
hard to take that first step but the
overall thing I would say is you know
you as an IT professional will have a
set of experiences and a set of
knowledge that other people don't have
and I think one of the things it's
really difficult to get your head around
when you first start thinking about this
is oh like I know this but that's
because it's obvious everyone must know
this thing and it's not true and so
often really it's having a confidence to
go I wonder if there's something here I
wonder if there's something interesting
try the idea IDE out with somebody that
you like that you trust and see what
comes back but as I say it's very much I
think about just being brave enough to
take that first step and accept the idea
that you probably have stuff to say that
other people would be interested in
hearing you know we all have to start
somewhere if you're a slightly more
senior programmer then you've got
experiences that a junior programmer
will learn from so learning how to share
that is a really really good skill in
networking theme you also have a
shortcut on getting involved with the
community and contributing to open
source how does contributing to open
source help enhance an engineer's career
it varies a little bit it's certainly
one of those things where if you think
about getting a job then being able to
point to an open source project that
you've contributed to is helpful it's a
little bit like it's an addition to your
CVO to your resume but I think there's
actually another reason to get involved
which is a little different to that
which is it teaches you how to fit in
with the style of somebody else's
project and when you work in a
professional context that's actually a
thing you have to do all the time so you
learn different ways to how to write
your code how to organize your code how
to build things and if you're contrib
say you're fixing a bug on an open
source project then doing that means
that your code fits in with the code
that's already there and you learn to do
that no matter what your personal
preference is
and it's a really fantastic learning
opportunity because that's such a
difficult thing to teach so you know
like an experienced University lecturer
can explain algorithms and languages and
all of those sorts of things really
really easily but what's much harder to
get across is things around aspects of
structure and taste and those sorts of
things that really start to matter on a
big project and they matter on a big
project because on any large project the
sort of fundamentals are down to
collaboration so that part of it I think
the other thing is you also learn
aspects of interaction so so often when
things break down in open source
communities it tends to be because
someone comes in with a very opinionated
view on a thing that doesn't fit with
the rest of the project and you have a
maintainer with a sort of broad mental
picture of how the thing should work and
you're coming in and suggesting a fix
but you have to fit in with their model
and you don't get to tell them that
they're wrong if you see what I mean a
lot of the way we learn to code actually
in the same way is how we learn to write
is through imitations it's learning how
to basically mimic another person's
writing style and gradually over time
you'll learn what works for you and what
you like and what you don't like so I
think learning how to adapt to people's
coding style is just such an invaluable
thing to do and I think that's kind of a
key part to it so the short answer is
it's a nice thing to be able to put on
your CV and that sounds like a good
reason but I actually think again
particular If you're sort of at that
relatively early stage in your career
and you haven't worked in a lot of
companies or worked on a lot of
different projects and that sort of
learning how to fit in is actually the
real benefit from doing it that said I
also want to say you don't have to do
this you know contributing code to an
open source project is time consuming
you're effectively doing work for three
I think it's a good thing to do but I
absolutely don't think if you've got
other polls on your time I don't know
maybe you've got young children or old
parents or something that you have to
look after if you've got other demands
your time that mean you can't do this
that should be understood too it's okay
but I do think it's helpful and as I
said I do think it's particularly
helpful when you start out because it
exposes you to a bunch of stuff you
won't learn as quickly any other way I
think is the best way I can put it what
are some best practices to get started
with open source contributions there are
lots of different ways to do it but I
think one of the things to do is to try
and start by choosing a project that you
actually use regularly and ideally with
a bug or something that you actually
want to try and fix keep in mind that
it's very easy as a programmer to think
the only thing I can contribute is code
but depending on what your strengths and
weaknesses are that might not be true so
you could think about might I start on
the
documentation most open source projects
suffer from poor documentation a lack of
documentation that can be a really good
place to start if you're good at ux
think about whether the ux might require
some help if you speak multiple
languages maybe you can translate stuff
from one language to another things like
EX accessibility graphic design
organizing meetups all of those things
are really important if you're thinking
about the project itself specifically
thinking about contributing to the
project there are going to be a bunch of
files that you need to read before you
start so there'll typically be a read me
there'll typically be a license there'll
typically be a file called something
like contributing or contributors which
sets out how the project likes to
receive contributions there should also
be a code of conduct and the code of
conduct will set out the behavior that's
welcome the consequences for unwelcome
behavior all of that sort of thing my
personal take is I am very reluctant to
get involved in any project that doesn't
have a code of conduct obviously that's
up to you your mileage may vary and all
that but if it does have a code of
conduct absolutely make a point of
reading it the project will also have an
issue tracker so that should allow you
to find what some of the issues are and
some projects have like a good first
issue tagged or something like that so
that can be a good easy sort of entry
point otherwise if that not the case
look for the smallest and easiest
contribution you can make so a you can
build up confidence and B you can kind
of establish a bit of a relationship
with the maintainers on the project the
other sort of plea I would make is
always keep in mind that being an open
source maintainer can be pretty
thankless you get lots of stuff some of
it's very well intentioned some of it
less so so always bear in mind amsource
maintainers are busy people they've got
a lot of difficulty you know a lot of
challenges on their time
again it sort of comes back to what we
were talking about with terms of empathy
try and imagine if I was the maintainer
on this project what are the things that
I would like to see in order to be able
to do whatever merge this in so yeah I
think those are probably the main ones
so think about how you're going to
contribute the right way to contribute
whether that's coding or ux or
documentation or whatever make sure you
read the foundational files the re the
license the contributing file the code
of conduct and then look for like a
small thing to start on so like a good
first bug or a minor contribution you
can make to get going I like your tip
about using documentation as an entry
point to get involved in open source
projects not many people are very
enthusiastic about writing documentation
so this could provide the path of least
resistance to get involved in open
source projects that provides us a good
Segway into the next theme of shortcuts
which is around do doation skills what
are some common mistakes engineers make
when creating
documentation and how can they be
avoided oh again that's a great question
it's quite a broad question to answer I
think one of the mistakes that people
often make is they don't think about who
they're writing
for so the very first thing to do is
to start by scoping out we typically
call it a Persona and writing but that's
maybe a little bit of a funny term to
use basically what you want to do is
start by identifying who your audience
is so knowing who you're writing for
will help you write in a way that's
appropriate for your
readership so most technology websites
most marketing departments will develop
these things called personas which
describe the audience you can kind of do
the same thing so Persona might consist
of a job title like Junior programmer
say an objective like learning how to
use the API and a set of assumptions
that you're making about this person so
I think my person is going to be
familiar with go I think they're going
to be comfortable following a set of
command line instructions I think
they're going to have a lot laptop
that's either running Windows or Macos
and has downloaded the SDK already once
you've got that in your head that really
then helps you to think about well what
does that person need to know and then
the other trick is always always favor
the reader so with that set of
assumptions it's a really good idea to
let them know up front what assumptions
you're making
and also to provide links to the other
resources so they can learn from those I
would also recommend defining what's in
scope for this particular document and
what it isn't so you know this is what
this document describes in detail the
API for our thing it does not describe
the underlying architecture and the
underlying architecture is described in
the architecture guide which you can
find here defining scope and nons scope
is really helpful because it allows you
as a writer it helps you stay on topic
but it's also helpful for the reader
because the reader knows what to expect
when they're reading your thing so
that's the place I would start other
common problems are things like using
terminology inconsistently or making
assumptions that everyone knows this
term so I won't explain it um if in
doubt always if you're using something
like an acronym always spell the acronym
out first you don't need to do that for
something like Ram or ROM or HTML or
whatever maybe but if you're not 100%
sure that your audience is going to know
it explain what you mean be very very
careful about using term consistently so
you know if you're referring to
something as protocol buffers don't
suddenly change to calling it Proto
Buffs partway through a paragraph
because some of your readers won't
understand that those two terms are
interchangeable so that's another common
one as an industry we're very fond of
three letter acronyms tlas and your
point with documentation is to convey
meaning so if you're overusing acronyms
you can end up making your document
really hard to read you just stand up
with a fact be like a it looks like a
bowl of alphabetic SC soup or something
so in that situation go back and spell
the abbreviations out in full watch out
for
consistency and try and be as clear and
concise as you possibly can be and that
takes work so I reference a book quite a
lot called on writing well which is by
somebody called William ziner and he has
this wonderful phrase he says the secret
of good writing is to strip your
sentence to its cleanest components and
basically your goal should be to get to
having the cleanest clearest sentence
that you can so in the same way that
when you're coding you want your code
your methods and your functions to be as
clearly defined as you can marriage and
as easy to follow as you can marriage
you want your sentences and your
paragraphs to work the same way the
other thing which I think people often
miss about writing is it's actually a
visual medium so people will see the
text on the page before they read any of
it and what that means is things like
length paragraph matters so if you have
very very long paragraphs particularly
at the beginning of something that can
feel a little bit intimidating
conversely if you have lots of one
sentence paragraphs that can be a bit
off-putting as well two or three
sentences is probably about optimal
funly enough it varies a bit so written
text is different from online with
written text you can get away with
slightly longer paragraphs than you can
with online text but yeah a lot of it is
thinking about consistency thinking
about conciseness and trying to be as
clear as you can possibly be and knowing
who your audience is up front I think
quite a few of these steps are also
useful in making effective presentations
there are strong parallels between the
two things I think so yes I have a whole
section on presentations and The
Business of writing a good presentation
and so on and I actually sat down and
chatted to both Holly cullings and
Trisha G who are both very very
experienced conference speakers as well
but yeah it's absolutely the same thing
the thing with a presentation you can
have a brilliant presentation but if
you're giving it to the wrong audience
it'll be a bad presentation right it
won't land because the audience either
it's too basic for them or it's
completely going over the top of their
heads and they've got no idea what
you're talking about so absolutely
understanding who the audience is is
really really important at the very
least you're going to want to know who
are they likely to be so am I looking
speaking to a bunch of Hands-On
developers am I speaking to bunch of
technical leaders Tech decision makers
how much experience are they all of
those sorts of things you know are the
developers at the conference more kind
of full stack or do they bias towards
backend development or front end
development is this a monot attack
audience like everybody is a Java
programmer or is it a more General sort
of architecture Cloud conference all of
those kind of things matter because it
lets you know what to pitch and what
you're going to explain and what you
don't need to explain and yeah I think
in general understanding the audience is
the absolute key thing really and then
other than that again there are quite
strong parallels so the different media
have different aspects about them so
whether that's podcasting or writing or
presenting or making videos on YouTube
or whatever it is they're obviously sort
of media specific aspects of them but
there are a lot of commonalities so if
you've learned one thing if you've
learned to write a blog well but
actually you'll find a lot of those
skills are applicable to presenting as
well we have covered a lot of ground
over here we have touched on all the
four themes before we close the session
I would like you to expand on the single
most valuable thing you have learned in
your career you touch on this in the
final section of your
shortcuts I think this is what you're
asking about there's a final piece of
advice I give and it's a piece of advice
that I got from my lovely mother and my
lovely mother knows nothing about
computers I don't think she might me
saying that she is very very very good
at people and when I was young I found
that baffling because I wasn't very good
at people and I sort of asked her about
it and she gave me various bits of
advice but the most useful bit of advice
she gave me was that most people are
really glad to help you provided you're
polite when you ask and at one level
that sounds sort of a bit trite and a
bit obvious and I certainly wasn't very
impressed about it when she first told
me it but I have to say that as I've got
older I've realized what an incredibly
astute piece of of advice that is so for
me personally the first time I did it
was about 30 years ago I was working in
an investment bank and I was automating
some stuff in Excel in Excel 5 I think
using VBA Visual Basic and we couldn't
get Excel to do what we wanted and I
ended up reaching out to a guy called
Eric Wells and he wrote a book called
developing Microsoft Excel Solutions and
I reached out to him he was a product
manager at Microsoft at the time and
said we're having this problem can you
help us and he sent me an email back
about a week later with an explanation
that not only explains how to solve the
problem but every related problem you
could think of and it was a very
Charming email and since then I've been
regularly quite astonished at how kind
and generous people are so industry
leaders in our industry the sort of
thought workers type people how kind and
generous they will be with their time
and how willing they are to share their
knowledge basically if you ask nicely at
the end of the day why wouldn't they be
we're all learning we're all trying to
improve this is a knowledge industry and
what that means is basically we're all
learning all the time so if there's
someone whose opinion you would value
reach out to them send them an email or
a message on LinkedIn or masteron or
whatever it is you choose and it's
entirely possible that they won't reply
but in my
experience most people will be more than
happy to help you if they possibly can
and the sort of flip side of that is you
should do the same thing so I have a
thing that I say a lot I've said it many
many times which is that as an industry
we are at our best when we share our
knowledge and that's basically how we
drive our industry forward is we share
what we know with each other and so if
there's stuff that you know think about
how you can share that whether that's
speaking at a conference or writing a
blog or whatever it is doesn't really
matter how you go about it but share
that knowledge and pass it on and yeah
absolutely seek out people whose
opinions you would value and ask them
you know have you got five minutes I
want to talk something through obviously
it's easier if youve know someone if you
go to conferences and you meet people
that can be helpful but even if not you
know people email me fairly regularly
and as far as I possibly can I always
try and make time and most people I know
are the same so yeah reaching out is a
good and underrated thing that's a gem
of an advice and if there's one thing
that you take away from this session it
will be this last piece of advice which
is if you need help don't hesitate to
reach out and ask for it most people in
our industry will be more than happy to
help you and with that we come to an end
to the session this is Brides amanat for
software engineering
radio thanks for listening to SC radio
an educational program brought to you by
it e software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at se-
radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter
or through our slack Channel at
seo. slack.com you can also email us at
team
e-r. this and all other episodes of SC
radio is licensed under creative
commment license
2.5 thanks for listening